A Guide to the Linton Massey Papers Relating to the William Faulkner Collection and the William Faulkner Foundation, 1953-1974
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6271-ai
Linton Massey Papers Relating to the William Faulkner Collection and the William Faulkner Foundation 1926-1974
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6271-a
ca. 1050
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There is no access to the papers by members of the public at this time.
There are no restrictions on access to the Library's microfilms of the William Faulkner manuscripts in its custody; the microfilm may be consulted by any interested party, and it will be lent through the interlibrary loan system. Materials are constantly added. Long-term loans may be arranged. Use of the microfilm will be restricted to the premises of the borrowing library. No loans will be made to individuals. Researchers should enquire of the Manuscripts Division concerning availability of microfilm of manuscripts that are pertinent to their work. Most of the literary manuscripts in our collections written by Faulkner, both holograph and typescript, have also been published in facsimile in William Faulkner Manuscripts, 25 vols (New York: Garland, 1986-87).
By the terms of the agreement by which the William Faulkner Foundation transferred the original manuscripts to the University, access to the original manuscripts is restricted (to ensure the survival of the physically-delicate originals) to doctoral candidates at the dissertation stage of their programs, and to certain mature scholars and critics. But even these researchers must demonstrate need to see the originals that goes beyond the requirements of most routine research. A doctoral candidate at the dissertation stage, or other qualified researcher who believes that his or her work requires access to the originals must correspond with the Curator of Manuscripts prior to arrival at the Library to obtain permission for access.
No microfilm, electrostatic, or other types of copies may be made of materials written by William Faulkner that are in our William Faulkner Collections. Other materials in the collections may be copied subject to the normal rules of the Library established under the conditions of the Copyright Act. All copying is performed by the Printing Services Department of the University.
Acquisition Information
The papers were loaned to the Library by Mrs. Linton R. Massey, executor of Mr. Massey's estate, on November 1974.
Scope and Contents
The Linton R. Massey Papers consist of ca. 1050 items (ca. 3 linear feet), 1926-1974, and concern only two aspects of Mr. Massey life: his collection of material for the William Faulkner collection at the University of Virginia Library; and his work as president of the William Faulkner Foundation. The first group includes correspondence with Faulkner scholars (especially biographer Joseph Blotner) and with fellow collectors, as well as some miscellaneous material. The papers from his period as president of the Foundation include correspondence about the Foundation scholarships and awards to students and novelists, access and use of the Faulkner manuscript, and the general business and financial records of the Foundation.
Organization
The papers have been kept in the two groups in which they were found in Mr. Massey's library study after his death. The division between the two groups, the personal papers and those of the Foundation, is not distinct, and the researcher is advised to examine both for any topic of interest. Each group is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Item Listing
- Series I: Papers and Correspondence of Linton R. Massey concerning his Faulkner Collection.
  - Addresses and Miscellaneous Notes re the William Faulkner Collection (Box Box 1)
  - Bibliographical Notes for the William Faulkner Collection, and Notes for an exhibition, 1957 and n. d. (Box Box 1)
  - Bibliographies of William Faulkner materials, 1957-1960 (Box Box 1)
  - Bibliographies (Photocopies) of William Faulkner Materials, n. d.; 5 folders (Box Box 1)
  - A - B, 1952-1972; ca. 50 items (Box Box 2)
  - Joseph Blotner, 1963-1973; ca. 35 items (Box Box 2)
  - Cleanth Brooks, 1960-1968; ca. 17 items (Box Box 2)
  - Matthew Bruccoli, 1950-1971; ca. 50 items (Box Box 2)
  - C, 1955-1974; ca. 16 items (Box Box 2)
  - Marguerite A. Cohn, 1949-1971; ca. 16 items (Box Box 2)
  - D, 1960-1963; 25 items (Box Box 2)
  - Albert Erskine, 1962-1974; ca. 16 items (Box Box 2)
  - F, 1957-1973; ca. 17 items (Box Box 2)
  - G, 1957-1971; ca. 30 items (Box Box 2)
  - H - J, 1957-1964; ca. 22 items (Box Box 2)
  - K - L, 1953-1970; ca. 25 items (Box Box 2)
  - M, 1953-1972; ca 70 items (Box Box 3)
  - N - O, 1957-1967; 28 items (Box Box 3)
  - P, 1957-1974; ca 38 items (Box Box 3)
  - R, 1957-1973; ca. 52 items (Box Box 3)
  - S, 1962-1974; ca. 85 items (Box Box 3)
  - T - V, 1960-1966; ca. 65 items (Box Box 3)
  - University of Virginia, 1953-1962; ca. 75 items (Box Box 3)
  - University of Virginia - Library, 1963-1974; ca. 100 items (Box Box 4)
  - University of Virginia - Miscellaneous, 1960-1964; ca. 10 items (Box Box 4)
  - W - Y, 1957-1968; ca. 35 items (Box Box 4)
  - Unidentified, 1962, n. d.; 5 items (Box Box 4)
  - Exhibition: AMs, TMs, William Faulkner Man Working 1919-1959, 1962; ca 15 items (Box Box 4)
  - List of Faulkner Material shipped to Princeton, 1957 Aug 30; 2 items (Box Box 4)
  - Lists of Faulkner items wanted by Linton Massey, 1957-1963; ca. 40 items (Box Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials re Faulkner, 1957-1972; ca. 35 items (Box Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous, 1959-1972; 10 items (Box Box 4)
  - Photocopies of "The Faulkner Feuds," "Warren, the Man to Watch,", 1956, 1964; 2 items (Box Box 4)
  - Photocopy of the Japanese and Arabic Title pages of The Reivers and Sartoris, 1953, 1963 (Box Box 4)
  - Photocopy of "Monk" by William Faulkner, n. d.; 1 item (Box Box 4)
  - Photocopy of William Faulkner's Will, 1960 Oct 30 (Box Box 4)
  - Photocopy of page 1 of "The Marionettes", n. d. (Box Box 4)
  - Photograph of Faulkner, 1926; 1 item (duplicates photo 0248) (Box Box 4)
  - Transcription of "The Golden Book of Jefferson and Yoknapatawpha County in Mississippi as compiled by William Faulkner of Rowanoak," Notes by Emily Iszak, 1932, 1966, 1967 (Box Box 4)
- Series II: Papers of Linton R. Massey as President of William Faulkner Foundation
  - Access to the Faulkner Papers, 1950-1974; 2 folders (Box Box 1)
  - Acquisitions of Faulkner Items by the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1974 (Box Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation of the William Faulkner Foundation, John Cooke Wylie's copy and duplicate, 1960 Dec 29 (Box Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation of the William Faulkner Foundation, Mr. Massey's copy. Also newspaper clippings., 1960 Dec 29 (Box Box 1)
  - Associates' Plan of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1967-1970; 3 folders
  - Award of the William Faulkner Foundation to Latin American Students, 1964-1969 (Box Box 2)
  - Distribution of Foreign Editions of Faulkner Novels, 1962 (Box Box 2)
  - Duplication of William Faulkner Foundation Minute Book (includes photocopies of deposit lists, correspondence, and newspaper clippings), 1960-1966 (Box Box 2)
  - Entries for Volume II of the William Faulkner Catalogue, n. d. (Box Box 2)
  - Financial Matters of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1970 (Box Box 2)
  - General Business of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1960-1969 (Box Box 3)
  - Ibero-American Novel Awards, 1961-1970 (Box Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1957-1968 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, John Knowles, 1960, 1962 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Lawrence Hall, 1961, 1961-1962 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Reynolds Price, 1962, 1961-1961 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Thomas Pyncheon, 1963, 1964-1965 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Charles Simmons, 1964, 1965-1967 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Cormac McCarthy, 1965, 1965-1967 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Robert Coover, 1966, 1967 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Robert Stone, 1967, 1968 (Box Box 3)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, Frederick Exley, 1968, 1964-1969 (Box Box 4)
  - Notable First Novel Winner, General, 1960-1971 (Box Box 4)
  - Notes and Minutes of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1970 (Box Box 4)
  - Papers re William Faulkner, Man Working 1919-1962, 1963-1970 (Box Box 4)
  - Papers re Plaque of the William Faulkner Foundation, 1961-1966 (Box Box 4)
  - Scholarship Correspondence: Excluding Individuals' Applications and Recommendations, 1961-1969 (Box Box 4)
  - Scholarship Correspondence: Student Applications and Recommendations, 1960-1969 (Box Box 4)